<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A comfortable treatise for the reliefe of such as are afflicted in conscience]</title>
            <author>Linaker, Robert, 1550 or 51-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836125</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836125</idno>
            <idno type="VID">377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05517)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1354:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A comfortable treatise for the reliefe of such as are afflicted in conscience]</title>
                  <author>Linaker, Robert, 1550 or 51-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>[Perused the second time and enlarged].</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Valentine Simmes for R. Boyle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Valentine Simmes worked as a printer in London ca. 1585-1622.</note>
                  <note>Includes dedication to Earl of Essex.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page lacking. Title, edition statement and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages torn, with marginal print lost on pages 6, 10, 15-16, 21-22 and 26.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right honorable my verie good Lord, Robert Deuoreux, Earle of Eſſex and Ewe, <hi>Vicount of Hereford, Lord Ferrers of</hi> Chartley, &amp;c. Maſter of the Queenes Maieſties horſe, knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maieſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable priuie Counſel, the continuall encreaſe of Gods euerlaſting fauour, peace and comfort in this, and in the world to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anie men (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) when they intend ſome euil, I meane when they haue reſolued free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and boldly to trade in ſome ſinne without check and control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doe ſeeke to ſhroude themſelues vnder the cloth and countenaunce of ſome great perſons of Worſhip and Honour. If my purpoſe or practiſe were ſuch, I might iuſtly feare to bee
<pb facs="tcp:377:2"/>croſſed and curſed in this my enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. The ſearcher of all hearts know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that my purpoſe, prayers, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours (through his gracious aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) are, and ſhall bee, to keepe a good conſcience in my miniſterie, to walke in the vprightneſſe of my heart, and to bee kept blameleſſe to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Ieſus Chriſt. In this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may it ſeeme good vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as you haue alreadie (at the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and humble ſute of manie my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good and worſhipfull friends) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued me to fauour: ſo ſtill to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your moſt honourable protection for my further encouragement in well doing. May it alſo pleaſe your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and religious diſpoſition, to comfort and countenaunce this Mite, and ſmall meaſure of comfort, which according to grace receiued, I haue once addreſſed, and now the ſecond time publiſhed, and enlarged for the reliefe of ſuch as grieue and groane vnder the heauie but then of their ſinnes. Behold I preſume to preſent it vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as the beſt preſent I haue, to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my humble dutie, ſeruice, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:377:2"/>And if by Gods good fauour and bleſsing there ſhall be ame one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, worde, ſyllable, or letter, which may bring, or adde comfort to you or yours, I ſhall be occaſioned the rather, heartily to bleſſe God for ſo great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and to pray more inſtantly, that your Honour may be bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your honours moſt humble and bounden ſeruant in the Lord,</hi>
Robert Linaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:377:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:377:3"/>
            <head>A COMFORTABLE TREATISE FOR THE reliefe of ſuch as are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in conſcience.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not long ſince I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you ſome ſmall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my hearty deſire to affoorde you ſome comfort, oncerning the inwarde affliction of your minde, if the Lord ſhould any way enable me thereunto. I haue now therefore (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of grace receiued) performed that my promiſe, as you ſhall vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by reading theſe leaues follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Whereby if you ſhall reape ſo much comfort, as from the depth of my heart, I entreat the Lord you may, I ſhal account my ſelfe for euer moſt nearely bound by all maner of dutie, and thankfulneſſe vnto his bleſſed maieſty. Howſoeuer it fall out, you ſhall receiue and keep this poore trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe by you, as an vndoubted record of my good meaning towards you, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of whoſe particular eſtate I haue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:377:4"/>ſome certaine knowledge, and for whome I pray moſt heartily,
<note place="margin">Inward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are neither common nor eaſie.</note> as I do for you.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe your afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nor eaſie to be born. And that bicauſe it is not outward, but inward, not of the body but of the minde. For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaieth, <hi>A ſorrowfull minde drieth the bones.</hi> Prouerbs <hi>17.22.</hi> Againe, <hi>A man will ſuſtaine his infirmitie, but a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t who can beare it?</hi> Prou. <hi>18.14.</hi> His meaning is, that no outward griefe or diſcommoditie whatſoeuer, but may be indured, and borne with great pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſtancie, but if the conſcience be wounded, and ſtriken with the feeling of Gods wrath for ſin, or any other great cauſe, there is neither man nor woman which is able to endure, and beare it out long, without great &amp; gracious aſſiſtance from God. That this is ſo, you can ſpeak of your own experience, yet for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, remember that you are not alone, the due conſideration whereof may not a little cheere vp your heart. For you reade of ſome in the ſcriptures, ſome you heare of, and ſome you know your ſelfe, who grone vnder the ſame burden, whoſe conſciences are ſet very hard vpon the racke, &amp; whoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:377:4"/>poore ſoules are in little eaſe, as well as yours.</p>
            <p>This is one principall point,
<note place="margin">A principal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled minde.</note> which I would haue you thinke vpon continually, but then eſpecially, when Sathan woulde beare you down, that you are alone in this kinde of affliction, and that no body is ſo troubled as you are. For this purpoſe you may remember that ſweete ſentence of the holy apoſtle,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.9.</note> wherein he doeth you to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <hi>that the ſame afflictions which you endure, are alſo accompliſhed and ſuffered of your other bretheren which are abroad in the world:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, let not ſuch a thought as this is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſway you,
<note place="margin">The beſt affected are your partners</note> that you ſhould think you haue no fellowes. For there bee a number of Gods deere childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who are as much and as often troubled with the ſame griefe of minde aſwell as you. For as there is no man ſo wiſe, ſo ſtrong, or ſo rich, but there be many as wiſe, as ſtrong, and as weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie: ſo there is none ſo greatly grieued in body or minde, but there be many who are as deepe in the ſame griefe as they be. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<note place="margin">Another chiefe comfort againſt Sathans tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> if your wily enimy ſhal by this kind of temptation aſſay to wound your weake conſcience, that you belong not to God,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:377:5"/>becauſe the correction is ſo ſharpe, and the rod wherwith you are beaten ſo ſmarting, you may boldly ſtep to him, wring his weapon out of his hand, &amp; therwith thruſt him thorow: for the maner of your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ement doeth proue verie ſtrongly to your conſcience, that you are highly in Gods fauor, and that becauſe you are not only partaker of that correction wherof all the ſonnes and daughters of God are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers (for <hi>ſo many as are without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection are baſtards &amp; not children</hi>) but of that kind of chaſticement,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abr. 12.8.</note> which only is proper to thoſe, who aboue many others haue bin in greater fauor with God. For example, Dauid was a man (as you haue learned from the ſcriptures) <hi>according to Gods own hart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dauid was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loued of God, and grieuouſly afflicted.</note> that is, ſuch a one as the Lord ſet great ſtore by, he notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was throughly whipt with this three ſtringed whip, as you may read at large not in one but in many Pſalmes, by name the ſirt Pſalme throughout, a great part of the two and twentieth, the eight and thirtie the whole Pſalme, the one and fiftie, and manie moe, which you maie find by diligent reading in the booke of the Pſalmes, where you ſhall vndeſtand
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:377:5"/>that his eſtate is all one with yours.</p>
            <p>Againe you may remember that Paul the Apoſtle was a choſen veſſell,
<note place="margin">Acts 9.15. Galat. 1.15. Paul a choſen veſſell ſharply handled.</note> 
               <hi>whom God had ſeparated from his mothers wombe:</hi> and therewithall you can not bee ignorant, how ſharply he was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, when the meſſenger of <hi>Sathan was ſent to boxe and buſſet him verie ſore,</hi> and that for a long ſeaſon: ſo that although he praied often and earneſtly,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12, 7, 8, 9.</note> yet could he not be deliuered. This only he receiued as an anſwer from the Lord, <hi>that his grace ſhould be ſufficient to vnderprop and ſtay him in his greateſt temptation, for my power</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is made perfect tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row weakneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paſſe not by this example without ſome good medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> In this reſolution he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted himſelfe as well contented, vntill ſuch time as the Lord ſhould grant him full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe. Theſe are choiſe examples of choiſe perſons,
<note place="margin">Trouble of mind a great priuilege of Gods fauour.</note> and not many ſuch to be ſound in the whole bodie of the Scripture: that you may conſider how great a priuilege of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour God hath voucheſafed vpon you, to make you equall with his deareſt children, and that in ſuch afflictions, as for their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of them, they are aboue many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands moſt renoumed. But why ſtand I vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe examples, when as Ieſus Chriſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:377:6"/>himſelfe <hi>(being the ſonne and heire in whom onely the Father is moſt highly well pleaſed)</hi> was not onely in meaſure and mercie thus chaſtiſed as you are,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17. The Sonne of God moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</note> but as we ſay commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, beaten without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yea hee was turned and beaten, ſo as through the exceeding great anguiſh of his ſeule,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.44.</note> he ſweat ſuch a ſweat in the garden, as neuer man ſweat the like, that is, drops like drops of blood, trickling downe to the ground.
<note place="margin">your affliction is but a flea b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing to that which your Sauior hath ſuffered for your ſake, that you might haue caſe.</note> Yea further, being brought and hanged vpon the croſſe (beſide all the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e offered and done to him by the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious cruel Iewes) his owne father hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him ſo extremely, not like a father, but as a moſt iuſt iudge, that he could not any longer bite in his griefe, but in great bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe he breakes out into theſe wordes ſauoring of deepe deſpaire,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27 46.</note> 
               <hi>my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Theſe words, I ſay, ſauor ſtrongly of deſpaire, becauſe he cries out that <hi>God had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him:</hi> yet was he farre from deſpaire, becauſe in the greateſt conflict with Hell and Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han, his whole truſt was in God, and therefore with great confidence, not once, but againe he doubleth his ſpeach ſaying, <hi>My God, my God.</hi> Thus you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:377:6"/>haue not onely many of the faithfull, but the ſonne of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (clad in your nature) more then a partner with you in your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> which I haue alleadged to this end, that you may know that as <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things worke for the beſt to thoſe that loue God,
<note place="margin">The ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rpeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worke the ſweeteſt comfort.</note> euen to them that are called of purpoſe:</hi> ſo this affliction of yours, which becauſe it is ſo ſharp, ſhal therefore worke your good a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deale the rather. For, experience teaheeth, that that purgation which for the time doth work moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and putteth the patient to the greateſt paine, doth in the end bring the moſt eaſe to him who hath receiued it.
<note place="margin">One exception.</note> But it may be you will take exception againſt this laſt example of Chriſt Ieſus, and ſay that hee was not ſo tormented for his owne, but for your ſinne,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.15. 1. Iohn 2.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he was without ſinne.</hi> Therein you ſpeake moſt truly for the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">Rom 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>Hee was deliuered to death for our ſinnes,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, whatſoeuer griefe or torment hee endured liuing, or dying, hee endured it for our ſakes, that the whole fruit &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort therof might redound to vs. And to this agreeth that which is written in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24.</note> Who his owne ſelfe bare our ſins
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:377:7"/>in his bodie on the tree, that we being deliuered from ſinne, ſhould liue in righteouſneſſe, by whoſe ſtripes we are healed.</hi> From henceforth therefore may you reape no ſmall comfort, for the peace of your conſcience in the greateſt heate of temptations.
<note place="margin">Chriſt hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred the torments of hell, that we might not ſuffer them, yea, that you may neuer ſuffer them.</note> For in as much as he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not for his owne, but for your ſinne, you may be therfore well aſſured that you ſhall neuer taſte of thoſe helliſh torments, which your ſinnes haue deſerued, and that becauſe your ſuretie, your media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, your Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt hath in your nature, but in his owne perſon (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the vttermoſt of Gods iuſtice) ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them for you, that you might neuer luffer them, but be fully and for euer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, both in this world, and in the world to come. For as the Apoſtle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Another excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain I know wel you wil thus reply that you will grant,
<note place="margin">To be in Chriſt Ieſus is true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines to him or her which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereof.</note> there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> muſt needes be true. But all the doubt lies in this, whether you your ſelfe bee in Chriſt Ieſus or not. For of that cannot you be perſuaded. If you could be aſſured therof,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:377:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>then you would not doubt, but you were without all danger of condemnation. But this is one point, which doth work no ſmal trouble in your conſcience. Go to then, let this be one chief point to deal with you in.</p>
            <p>And firſt to begin withall, let me aſk you this one queſtion. And I do not only pray,
<note place="margin">A great charge.</note> but on Gods behalfe for his glory, and the good of your ſoul, I charge you to anſwer me plainly &amp; truly.
<note place="margin">Once aſſured and euer aſſured of ſaluation.</note> Had you euer any aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſaluation in al your life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were you euer perſuaded by the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word to be ſaued by the death of Chriſt Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">An vnſained ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for ſinne, a deadly hatred, a ſound purpoſe of amendment, are vndoubted ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks of Gods childe.</note> did you euer feel the power of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in your ſoule by theſe marks, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you were more greeued &amp; ſorie at the heart for your ſins, then for any thing in the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le world: did you, and doe you beare a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hatred againſt them,
<note place="margin">2. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.9, 10, 11</note> as againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell himſelfe: did you, and doe you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the vttermoſt of your power, to forbeare and forſwear the practiſe of them all,
<note place="margin">Luke 7.15. See you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſwer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to euerie artiele truely as you will anſwere at you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perill.</note> and to walke in holineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe all the dayes of your life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> did that worde which you haue heard ſo long, ſo ſoundly, and ſo powerfully preached to your conſcience,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.2. Phil. 3.8.</note> which you reade ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> meditate and take ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:377:8"/>great delight as that you count al worldly things but dung in compariſon thereof: did that word, I ſay, neuer ſpeake peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablie to your conſcience by the holy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie? did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neuer giue you aſſurance and ioy in the holy Ghoſt: did it neuer worke ſuch ſweete comfort, as no worldly ioy could be like vnto it: did you neuer heare ſuch a ſermon from your owne godly and carefull paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or, or from any other, that you haue ſaid at your comming home, you would not for all the worlds good but you had heard it, becauſe it was ſo ſweete, and comfortable: did you neuer ſpeake that worde, from the true feeling of the heart, which might warrant your ſoule, that you are in Chriſt Ieſus? If this worde hath had this gracious and powerfull worke in your ſoule (as I am fully perſwaded it hath,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30.</note> and your ſelfe cannot denie it: for if you doe, beſide the great wrong you offer your own ſoule, you treſpaſſe againſt that ſpirit, whereby you haue bene ſealed vnto the day of redemption) then know aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you are ſo gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body of Chriſt Ieſus,
<note place="margin">Gods loue is euerlaſting and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>changeable.</note> as nothing ſhall be able to ſeperate you from that loue which the Lord your God beareth you in his deare Sonne, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:377:8"/>whome hee hath ſo loued you once,
<note place="margin">Iohn 13.1.</note> as hee muſt needes loue you for euer. And that bicauſe the Euangeliſt ſaith, <hi>whome hee loues he loues to the end.</hi> For <hi>the gifts and calling of God are without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Againe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>God is not as man that hee ſhould lie,
<note place="margin">Num. 23.19.</note> neither as the ſonne of man that hee ſhould repent. Hath he ſaide, and ſhall he not do it? and hath he ſpoken it, and ſhall hee not accompliſh it?</hi> No, be you well aſſured, and write vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.29.</note> 
               <hi>that the ſtrength of Iſrael wil not lie nor repent.</hi> For, as the apoſtle Iames ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>with him there is no variableneſſe nor ſhadowing by turning.</hi> Let theſe and ſuch like places be alwais in your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and giue your ſelfe vnto the continuall meditation thereof. For they ſhall ſtand you in great ſtead, if you can call them to minde, when your temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhal aſſaile you with greateſt ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. And forget not,
<note place="margin">Therefore reade them often and continually that you may alwayes haue them at your fingers end.</note> often to thinke of ſuch excellent places as that is, which you find written in the eight chapter of the Epiſtle written to the Romanes, and the ſixe and thirtieth verſe, after this manner, <hi>What ſhal ſeparat vs from the loue of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation or anguiſh, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:377:9"/>or famine, or nakedneſſe, or peril, or ſword, &amp;c.</hi> No, <hi>I am perſuaded, that neither death nor life, angels nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any creature ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And full ſweet to this purpoſe are thoſe words of the holie prophet Dauid.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>The Lorde is neere vnto them that are of a contrite heart, and will ſaue ſuch as be afflicted in ſpirit. Great are the troubles of the righteous: but the Lorde deliuereth him out of them all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note> Againe, <hi>weeping may abide at euening, but ioy commeth in the morning.</hi> But you finde no ſuch matter you ſaie, for this trouble of minde hath holden you, not onelie nights and daies, but weekes and moneths, yea and yeeres, and yet you can finde no eaſe nor comfort. Be it ſo, yet bee not therefore out of heart, for the longer it bee before you haue eaſe, the more welcome it ſhal be when it commeth. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are the wordes of the Wiſe-man where hee ſaieth, <hi>The hope that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, is the fainting of the heart, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:377:9"/>when the deſire commeth it is a tree of life.</hi> Laſtly, let the words of Eliphas the Temanite be faſt bound vnto your ſoule, which you ſhall find thus reported in the booke of Iob, the fiſt chapter 17, 18, 19. verſes. <hi>Beholde, bleſſed is the man whome God correcteth: therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe not thou the correction of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. For hee maketh the wound and bindeth it vp: hee ſmiteth, and his handes make whole. Hee ſhall deliuer thee in ſixe troubles, and in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth the euill ſhall not touch thee.</hi> The ſumme &amp; drift of all that which hath bin ſet downe from the beginning to this preſent place, is to encourage you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the maner of your affliction, which though it be very ſharp &amp; bitter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, becauſe <hi>no chaſtiſement for the preſent ſeemeth to be ioyous but greeuous:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 12.11. A principal co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoule.</note> yet <hi>there is a time, when it ſhall bring the quiet fruit of righteousneſſe vnto them that are exerciſed thereby.</hi> In regard hereof Moſes the man of God ſaith,
<note place="margin">Deut. 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>that the Lord humbled his owne choſen people and prooued them, that hee might doe them good at their latter ende.</hi> And truely, in my poore iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:377:10"/>you may gather more vndoubted aſſurance of Gods euerlaſting fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your ſoule by theſe inward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">Afflictions bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter tokens of Gods loue then riches and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie.</note> then by any outward proſperitie of anie worldly bleſſing whatſoeuer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of health, of riches, or ſuch like. And that, becauſe in theſe your afflictions you are moſt like vnto your head Chriſt Ieſus,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.2.</note> who though <hi>hee were the right ſonne and heire of the whole world: yet had hee not a houſe to hide his head in,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 8.10.</note> as himſelfe confeſſeth.
<note place="margin">Hebr. 2.10.</note> But it pleaſed the Father <hi>(ſeeing hee would bring manie children vnto glorie) to conſecrate the prince of their ſaluation through afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Now, as the holy Apoſtle reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 2.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>This is a true ſaying, if we be dead with him, we ſhal alſo liue with him. If we ſuffer with him, we ſhal alſo reigne with him.</hi> To be ſhort, the Holy ghoſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> 
               <hi>That we muſt by many afflictions enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> And once againe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe whom he knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hee alſo predeſtinated to be made like to the Image of his Sonne, that he might be the firſt-borne among many brethren.</hi> So that you may wel perceiue you are not thus farre forth, any whit out
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:377:10"/>of your way, but you keepe the rode,
<note place="margin">Afflictions the highway to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the good way which leaveth you as ſtreight as a line vnto the kingdome of heauen. And therefore as no traueller, who keepes his right way and knowes it, wil be ſory, but very glad, becauſe he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to come to that place, where his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is to abide: ſo no more cauſe haue you to be grieued, but rather to reioyce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you know you walke in the ſtreight path, which ſhal bring you to that place of your abode, where you would ſo faine be, and where you ſhal abide moſt bleſſed and happie for euer. Thus much haue I thought good to offer vnto your godlie meditations, to encorage you concerning the maner of your afflictions. The Lord grant you a rich portion of his ſpirite, that your ſoule may reape a gratious bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Now you ſhall further vnderſtand in few wordes, what ſhall be the ſubſtance of all the matter which foloweth in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of this poore treatiſe.
<note place="margin">The ſubſtance of the whole Treatiſe follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> I purpoſe ſo neere as I can, to gather together thoſe obiections, which you and others doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt your ſelues: and ſo farre as the Lord ſhall affoord me his grace, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in order to anſwer them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:377:11"/>
The firſt and principall obicetion (ſo far as I can conceiue &amp; learne by conference with you,
<note place="margin">The firſt obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and anſwere.</note> and with ſo many as I haue any acquaintance) is this,
<note place="margin">The troubled minde doubts of Gods fauour.</note> That you doubt much of Gods fauour towards you; that you feare it greatly you are not the child of God, and if you be, yet can not you be thereof certainely perſwaded. This obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath aireadie beene anſwered in part: not withſtanding becauſe it is as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of al the other obiections, I will in hope of Gods gracious aſſiſtance indeuor my ſelfe to anſwere it more fully, for your better contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Firſt therfore I would gladly learne this one thing of you, or of anie other (who is your partner in theſe temptations) who it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beareth you ſo greatly in hand,
<note place="margin">A needefull point therefore marke it well.</note> you are not the child of God. If you anſwer, your conſcience, through the greatneſſe of your ſinne doth tel you ſo: then do I againe demaund of you, who it is that ſets your conſcience a worke to vrge this point &amp; to what end.
<note place="margin">Harken to Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for he ſeckes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God.</note> If it be Gods ſpirit, you may be right glad, becauſe then it is for your good, namely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you may go out of your ſelfe, &amp; ſecke the forgiueneſſe of your ſinnes and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſaluation in Chriſt his death and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:377:11"/>to the full aſſurance of Gods fauor, and the euerlaſting peace of your conſcience.
<note place="margin">Hearken not to ſathan, for he hath vowed your deſtruction.</note> But ſpeake the truth, is it not rather a ſtrong temptation of Sathan your deadly enemie to trouble the peace of your conſcience, and if it be poſſible, to driue you to deſperation. If it be ſo, as I feare it greatly, then ſay I vnto you, there is no cauſe why you ſhould beleeue him. Firſt becauſe he is a lyer.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> Secondly becauſe he is your enemie, who meanes you no good at al. That he is a lyar it is manifeſt, <hi>becauſe he hath beene ſo from the beginning,</hi> And he cannot nowe chaunge his nature. It is as much againſt his nature to ſpeake the truth, as it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that God ſhould lie,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18. Rom. 3.4.</note> who is onely &amp; euer true. Therefore, there is no cauſe why you ſhoulde beleeue ſuch a common liar as the Deuill (who will lie as faſt as a dogge can trot, as wee vſe to ſay in our common ſpeach. You haue iuſt cauſe therefore to except againſt him in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Againe, you neede not doubt that hee is your enemy,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.10. 1. Pet. 5.8.</note> and that to the death; becauſe hee <hi>is the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of the bretheren, and like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lion goeth about continually ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:377:12"/>whom he may deuoure.</hi> In regard whereof you are not to hearken to him,
<note place="margin">No credit to bee giuen to the deuil though he ſpeak the truth, bicauſe his meaning is badde.</note> or beleeue anie thing he ſhall ſaie vnto you, no although he ſpeake the trueth. And my reaſon is, becauſe he will not tell you the trueth, to helpe, but to hinder you, not to cheere, but to choake you, not to ſaue, but to ſpill your bloud. And whereas you will replie, you cannot denie, but hee ſaieth the trueth concerning the greatneſſe of your ſinnes, and that iuſt condemnation which you haue deſerued for them. I anſwere thereto after this manner. That you are not to take the knowledge of your ſinnes from Sathan, becauſe he will not tell you the trueth, and the whole trueth as it is in deede.
<note place="margin">Marke thed euils cunning.</note> For either he will pare your ſins, and make them leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be, to make you altogether careleſſe, or elſe hee will make them greater then they be, to throw you headlong into deſpaire. But you are to take the perſit knowledge of your ſins,
<note place="margin">The holy vſe of the Miniſterie.</note> from the true vnderſtanding of the Lawe of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.</note> faſt girded to your conſcience, by the holie miniſterie, which GOD hath ordained for this purpoſe,
<note place="margin">Regard and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erence the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie if you loue your ſoule.</note> that you maie thereby come to true and vnfained repentaunce of all your ſinnes, and bee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:377:12"/>ſaued through faith in Chriſt his blood. For <hi>the blood of Chriſt doth clenſe you from all ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.7.</note> And if you will yet reaſon againſt your ſelfe, that your ſinnes are ſo great, that you can gather no aſſurance of Gods fauour towards you:
<note place="margin">Examples of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious ſinners who repented and were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</note> then let mee offer to your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration ſome one or two examples of ſuch notorious knowne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as the world cried ſhame of, and yet repenting had their ſinnes forgiuen them. I meane of ſet purpoſe to make choiſe of thoſe perſons and people, who in the ſcriptures are noted to be moſt infamous. Becauſe you and ſuch as are ſo exerciſed as you are, doe indeed charge your ſelues further than you ought.
<note place="margin">No eaſie matter to comfort a troubled mind.</note> For you make your ſelues ſo bad, as though none were to be compared vnto you, or as though God had no mercie in ſtore for you. And hereupon it comes to paſſe, that almoſt there is not any word of God which can bring peace vnto your troubled conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. I intend therefore to match you ſo, and with ſuch, as you ſhall be forced to confeſſe you are outmatched. The end ſhal be this, to bring glad tidings to your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and ſorrowful ſoule, that God both is and will be more fauourable to you, then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:377:13"/>you can as yet be perſuaded. For if God haue ſhewed mercie to thoſe,
<note place="margin">Reaſons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their knowne ſins, were in all mens iudgement further from mercie: how can he denie you mercie,
<note place="margin">The Lord per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade your heart.</note> who neuer brake into that outrage of ſin, and yet doe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie ſue vnto him for mercie. That good maſter, who forgaue his bad ſeruant at his owne intreatte, ten thouſand talents, would not haue beene hard vnto him, who ought but a hundred pence, if he had ſued vnto him, as he did to his cruell and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull fellowe ſeruant, who by no meanes would bee entreated, to ſhewe that fauour in a little debt, which was ſhewed him in a verie great ſumme. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, I pray you, that you haue to deale with a God, who is farre more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull: and therefore you may bee ſure to find more fauour. You reade in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Saint Luke the ſeuenth chapter,
<note place="margin">Marie Magdalen a notorious and knowne ſinner.</note> from the thirtie and ſir verſe vnto the end of the chapter, of Marie Magdalen, and of her behauiour, being a woman not only vehementlie ſuſpected of lewde life, but openlie knowne for a common harlot, and generallie ſo taken, as may appeare by the wordes of Simon the Phariſie, who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:377:13"/>receiuing Jeſus Chriſt into his houſe,
<note place="margin">Luke 7.38, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> The hypocriſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Phariſie is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Chriſt.</note> thought neuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deale the better, but much the worſe of him, becauſe hee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo bad a woman to come ſo neare him, but eſpecially to lay any hande vpon him, as to waſh his feete with her teares, and to wipe them with the haires of her head: to kiſſe his feet, and to annoint them with aintment. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>this notwithſtanding,
<note n="1" place="margin">Ieſus Chriſt likes Maries doings.</note> marke what marueylous great mercie Jeſus Chriſt ſhewes to this ſo wretched and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man. Firſt he takes in very good part, whatſoeuer ſhe had done vnto him, whereas Simon looked he ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue ſhewed his great diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iking of her dealing, but to haue ſhaken her vp, &amp; that roundly for her ſawtines, to come ſo neare him without his loue and leaue. Secondly he is ſo farre off from miſliking her beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niour in that preſent action,
<note n="2" place="margin">Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maries reare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mons great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dinner.</note> that hee doth highly commend her to Simon, and that after ſo ſpecial a maner, that he giues him to vnderſtand he takes better liking of her kindneſſe, then of all the great prouiſion which he had made for him: becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocuer ſhe did, ſhe did it with an vpright heart towards him, and in a ſincere loue for the good of her own ſoule. Thirdly for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:377:14"/>the eaſe of her heart,
<note n="3" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies ſinnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>giuen her.</note> which nowe was grieuouſly tormented for her wicked life paſt (as appeared by the abundance of teares ſhe powred out) hee ſaith to Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in her hearing,
<note place="margin">Luke 7.47.4</note> that <hi>many ſinnes were forgiuen her.</hi> Fourthly, that ſhe might take better hold of his wordes,
<note n="4" place="margin">Chriſt ſpeakes particularly to Marie for her comfort.</note> and apply them to her ſelfe for the comfort of her owne ſoule, he turnes his ſpeach par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly vnto her, and ſaith in more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner,
<note place="margin">Verſe, 48.50.</note> 
               <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee, Thy faith hath ſaued thee.</hi> Laſtly, that ſhe might depart a ioyfull and bleſſed woman indeed, wanting nothing which might make for the peace of her conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<note n="5" place="margin">Maries happie farewell. Verſe 50.</note> he giues her a moſt ſweet farewell, ſaying, <hi>Go in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let mee reaſon a little with you,
<note place="margin">The application of the firſt example.</note> concerning this woman, can you when you haue ſtrained out your ſinnes to the vttermoſt, make your ſelfe as bad as this woman. No, you cannot, you may not, you dare not. For how dare you ſtaunder your owne ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Applie the plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the ſore that your ſoule may haue eaſe.</note> when it is not any way lawfull to ſtaunder another? and if you bee bound to tender the good name of your brother as well as your owne, then it muſt needes follow, you are by nature moſt bound to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:377:14"/>tender your owne. If then you cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but you are by great ovs outmatched in this example, ſhew me what ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you can bring to proue, why Ieſus Chriſt ſhould not entreat you as kindly, &amp; ſhew you as much fauour as he ſhe wed to Mary, eſpecially when as your ſins (euen by your own confeſſiou) are neither ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, nor ſo apparant, and open in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward tranſgreſſions, to be ſeene and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the world, as hers were.
<note place="margin">The teares you ſhed are not ſpile for the Lord hath put them all into his bottell.</note> And yet for all that your teares as manie, your hart as much tormented with ſorow, your kindneſſe as great to Chriſt in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and your deſire as great to be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie his at his commaundement. Did he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard her, and will he reiect you? did he not ſhew her a hard countenance, and will hee looke ſowrelie vpon you? did not ſhe let ſo much as anie one teare fall in vaine? did her teares moue him to compaſſion? and doe you thinke he will not haue pitie vpon you &amp; put vp all your teares into his bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> were many ſinnes forgiuen her, and can any of your ſins be vnpardoned? was her faith ſtrong to ſaue her, and ſhall your faith want ſtrength to ſaue you? did Chriſt for a farewell, bid her go in peace, and wil
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:377:15"/>he ſend you away emptie without peace? No verelie. If you thinke ſo, you thinke much amiſſe, and therfore ſuch a thought muſt not depart without ſom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">A familiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance.</note> Suppoſe there is a man of ſo great wealth, that hee knowes no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de of his goodes. And ſuppoſe that this man hath many debters, which owe him verie great ſummes of money. As for example, ſome owe him thouſands, ſome hundreds, and ſome many ſcores of pounds. Amongſt them al there is one poore man, who owes him twentie pounds, which hee is no way able to pay, nor anie pente thereof, if hee ſhould bee eaſt in priſon, and lie there till he rot. If this great rich man ſhall cauſe a proclamation to be made, that all and euerie one of his debters ſhould come to him, and he will frankly and freely forgiue them all. although the debt were neuer ſo great, vpon this condition, that they will confeſſe and acknowledge the debt to bee due, whether it were more or leſſe. If the poore man ſhould come in among the reſt of the debters, and confeſſe himſelf to owe him ſuch a ſumme as I haue named,
<note place="margin">He that forgiues a great debt, will readily forgiue a ſmall.</note> lay forth his pouertie, and therewithall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vpon his knees with teares beſeech
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:377:15"/>him to ſhewe ſome fauour toward him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhould not he in this caſe haue good hope to be forgiuen, eſpecially if before his face he ſhould ſee one to haue thouſands forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for a word of his mouth.
<note place="margin">Labour to apply if you deſire to haue comfort.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things concerne you verie near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and therefore I am ſo much the rather to intreat you, not to make waſh way of them, but as they do nearely concerne you and your good, ſo to lay them neare vnto your heart, by reuerent meditation, that your ſoule may finde a gracious and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable bleſſing.
<note place="margin">A ſecond exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the great rebellion of Iſrael.</note> The ſecond example whereof I would haue you to make dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent conſideration, is written in the firſt chapter of the prophet Eſay, and the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth verſ, where the Lord makes a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous large offer of great mercy vnto a people, who had highly offended him, I meane the people of Iſrael. To theſe Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites in moſt louing maner the Lord ſpeaketh, <hi>Come,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Eſai. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>let vs reaſon togither, though your ſinnes were as crimſon, they ſhall bee made white as ſnow, though they were red as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as wooll.</hi> What the offer is you heare, and how great it is, your ſelfe is able to iudge: euen ſo large an offer of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:377:16"/>mercy as none can be greater. In one word, it is as if the Lord ſhould ſay. O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael thou haſt ſinned againſt me thy good God moſt grieuouſly, and haſt deſerued that I ſhould not onely puniſh thee ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but for euer caſt thee cleane out of my fauour. Notwithſtanding vpon thine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance for all thy ſinnes paſt, and a reſolute and full purpoſe of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereafter,
<note place="margin">A general pardon offered.</note> I am content to forgiue &amp; forget them all, and to giue thee my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious generall pardon, to acquit and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thee of all and euerie one of thine iniquities, that not ſo much as anie one of them ſhall bee able to condemne thee in this world, or in that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Here I pray you conſider a little with me,
<note place="margin">The curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites.</note> the eſtate and condition of this people, at the time of this louing offer, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with alſo conſider, what cauſe there was why the Lord ſhould ſhew ſo great fauour to this people. Begin you at the ſecond verſe of the forenamed chapter, and marke aduiſedly what manner of complaint the Lord takes vp againſt them.
<note n="1" place="margin">An appeale to all the creatures of diſobedience.</note> Firſt hee calles heauen and earth with all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures therein to witneſſe their rebellion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:377:16"/>and diſobedience againſt him.
<note n="2" place="margin">Vnthankefulnes.</note> Secondly he challengeth them of ſo monſtrous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes, that it is too too ſhamefull: for he ſhewes they were ſo farre gone in this point, that the brute beaſts, euen the oxe and the aſſe, which were dumme and without reaſon, were more thankfull in theire kinde, to their owners for their fodder, then they were for ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of bleſſings, which he had beſtowed vpon them.
<note n="3" place="margin">A large indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Thirdly in the third verſe he draws out againſt them, a very ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all inditement both for words and matter, wherein he layes forth all their ill behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.3.</note> and paints them out in moſt liuely colours, calling them with great dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, <hi>A ſinnefull nation, a people laden with iniquitie, a ſeede of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, corrupt children.</hi> Fourthly,
<note n="4" place="margin">A proofe of the inditement.</note> hee prooues this inditement and euery part thereof, by charging them to their faces with murder, and blood, by reaſon of their horrible oppreſſion, and crueltie towards all in generall,
<note place="margin">Verſe 15.17.</note> but more ſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore, the widow, the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the fatherleſſe, all this is done in the fifteenth and ſeuenteenth verſes. In the practiſe of which ſinnes, and all other
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:377:17"/>kind of filthines, they were ſuch exquiſite workemen,
<note place="margin">Verſe 10.</note> that they were more like the people of Sodom and Gomorra (whom the Lord with fire from heauen deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) then that people whom the Lord had choſen,
<note place="margin">Exod. 29.5, 6</note> and pickt out from all the nations <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of the world, <note place="margin">Verſe 11.12.13.14.15.</note>to be a peculiar and a holie people vnto himſelfe. Fiftly, they were ſuch hollow hearted hypocrites in all the outward exerciſes of religion,
<note place="margin">Hypocrits in the ſeruiſe of God.</note> that the Lord deteſted all their ſacrifices, and vtterly abhorred all their praiers, as you may reade in the 11.12.13.14. and 15. verſes. To make an end with ſo bad a people, as lightly could not be worſe, they were ſo deſperate, and hardned in their wickedneſſe, that they were paſt cure, and no hope or verie ſmall (if anie at all of the greater part) of their amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, becauſe the Lord had aſſayed by all good meanes, to bring them to ſome goodnes. He had wooed them with bleſſings, and feared them with his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
<note place="margin">Sam. 7.14.</note> he had chaſtiſed them often with rods, and many times ſcorged them with the plagues of the children of men:
<note place="margin">Verſe 5.6.</note> but all in vaine, the more they were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, the worſe they were, and grew
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:377:17"/>to be more deſperate, as appeares out of the fift and ſixt verſes. After all this bad dealing, as though they had beene no ſuch leude and graceleſſe people, or as though they had not offended ſo grieuouſly,
<note place="margin">The Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treates peace at their hands which had highly offended him.</note> nay rather as though the Lord had done them ſome great wrong, he ſeekes to them (wheras they ſhould haue both ſued and ſought to him) that there might be a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of peace, and a ful reconciliation made betweene them. For which purpoſe he offers in moſt friendly and louing maner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to common with them, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Verſe 18.</note> 
               <hi>Come let vs reaſon together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe giue me leaue once againe to deale with your conſcience in this point. Charge your ſoule with as many ſinnes as euer you can poſſibly call to minde,
<note place="margin">A particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the former example.</note> in any parte of your life, either before or ſince your calling, in ignorance or in knowledge, in youth or in age, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, or with whom ſoeuer you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them, eithert by thought, word or deed, in the light of the day, or in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night. Bind them all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of them in one bundle, caſt them into the one end of the ballance: when you haue ſo done, take vp the ſinnes of this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:377:18"/>people, put them into the other ende and weigh them together without ante deceit. Nay, for this once you ſhall haue leaue to ſhew your beſt cunning, and ſee if you can make your ende heauier. If you can not (as I am ſure you can not, except you will vſe ſome notable deceit, which will be ſoone found out, ſo as you ſhall neuer be able to anſwere it) then knowe you, and let your conſcience alſo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<note place="margin">A ſtrong reaſon to proone and perſwade.</note> that if the Lord ſaide vnto a wicked people, froſen in ſinne, <hi>come,</hi> hee doeth much more ſaie to you, who woulde ſo faine leaue your ſinne, <hi>come,</hi> and againe <hi>come,</hi> let vs two reaſon together. For, although thy ſinnes be in thine own ſight as crimſon, yet ſhall they bee made as white as ſnowe, though they bee (to thy ſeeming) as redde as euer was the ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, yet they ſhall bee as white as anie wooll, becauſe they ſhall bee all ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſcowred and waſhed in the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as not any one of them ſhall be able to condemne thee, either in this world or in the world to come.</p>
            <p>And that you may bee the more bolde to come, behold your ſweet ſauiour <hi>(who being made ſin for you that you might
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:377:18"/>be made the righteouſneſſe of God)</hi> ſaith alſo vnto you,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>come:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11.28. Another reaſon of great weight: will you not come when your Sauiour calleth you for your good.</note> yea for your further encouragement be offers, and is readie to take you by the hand, and to go with you himſelfe vnto the father, for whoſe ſake you muſt needes be moſt heartely wellcome. And if you ſhall thus anſwere your Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, that gladlie you would come, but that your ſinnes doe ſo clogge, and loade your heart with ſorrow: then heare how againe he replies vpon you ſaying.
<note place="margin">The tired ſinner may boldely come to Chriſt.</note> If the caſe ſtand ſo with thee, then come in any wiſe, yea therefore the rather come. For if thy ſinnes doe put thee to paine, and be as a heauie burden, to bigge for thee to beare, come thy way, and ſay them all vpon my ſhoulders, for my backe is broade inough to beare them all, were they neuer ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. I am well content to beare the whole loade of them mine owne ſelfe, that thou mayeſt be fully and for euer diſcharged.
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.28. Marke well that Chriſt will ſaue humbled ſinners and none other.</note> For ſuch ſinners doe I call, and ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners onelie will I ſaue, as are in paine and throughlie tyred with their ſinnes. As for ſuch ſinners as haue ſtore of ſinnes hanging vpon them, and either doe not feele them, or care for no helpe, I haue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:377:19"/>nothing to do with them, neither will I be any Sauiour vnto them. For, <hi>the whole neede not the phyſition but the ſicke.
<note place="margin">Matth. 9.12, 13.</note> I came not to call the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but ſinners to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre I haue endeuoured to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie your firſt and maine obiection, and to my power aimed at this marke, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to pacifie your troubled conſcience with this comfortable and ſound perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> that <hi>beeing iuſtified by faith, you haue peace toward God through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, by whome you haue boldneſſe and entraunce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12.</note> and that by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull working of Gods ſpirite, <hi>which is the ſpirite of adoption which you haue receiued,
<note place="margin">Ro. 9.15, 16, 18.</note> whereby you crie Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Father. The ſame ſpirite beareth witneſſe with your ſpirit, that you are the childe of God. And if you bee a childe, then are you alſo an heire of God, and a ioynt heire with Chriſt.</hi> And therefore not I, but Gods holie ſpirite in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes (whoſe wordes you ought both to regard and reuerence) ſaieth vnto you in this wiſe:
<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs goe boldely vnto the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:377:19"/>throne of grace, that wee may receiue mercie and finde grace to helpe in time of neede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you marke aduiſedly that the author of the epiſtle calleth vpon you to goe, and to goe boldely.
<note place="margin">Labour to caſt off feare when God would haue you bolde.</note> But whither would hee haue you goe? forſooth to the throne. And to what throne?
<note place="margin">You are louingly called to come to a louely throne, hanged all ouer with hangings of grace and mercie.</note> Not to a throne of iuſtice, of wrath, and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but to a throne of grace and mercie. It is indeede a throne of iuſtice, of wrath, and condemnation, but not to you, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuch as you are. The throne againſt your comming is couered and hanged all ouer from end to end, both wide and ſide with moſt rich &amp; coſtly cloth of grace and mercy. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hangings are al of grace and throughout embrodered with nothing but mercie. View them your ſelfe, looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them throughly, and you ſhal finde all mercie and nothing els but mercie. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are willed to come to this throne boldly, becauſe it is a throne of grace and mercie. And that you may knowe before hand what you ſhall gaine by your comming thither,
<note place="margin">Mercie welcomes you.</note> you are told plainly &amp; truely, you ſhall find (that which your ſoul moſt longeth after) ſtore of grace,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:377:20"/>and you ſhall receaue ſo much mercy as may helpe you, when you ſhall ſtand in moſt neede of mercie. Thus muſt is needs be,
<note place="margin">you muſt needes be welcome, for the Iudge is your great frend.</note> and otherwiſe it cannot be, becauſe the iudge himſelfe, who ſits vpon the throne, is a iudge ful of mercie, clad alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with rich robes of mercy, and your great frend, who wil ſhew you all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fauo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that may be. For why, he is Ieſus your Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Matth. 1.21.</note> who will in no caſe ſuffer you to miſcarie.</p>
            <p>Here is good occaſion offered to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere a ſecond obiection of yours,
<note place="margin">The ſecond obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and anſwer.</note> which is, that you beleeue, that Ieſus Chriſt is a perfect and an able Sauiour, but not your Sauiour:
<note place="margin">The troubled minde cannot apply Chriſt to it ſelfe.</note> that he ſaith come, but he ſaith not come to you. But I will prooue he ſpeaketh to you as wel as to any other, and that as particularly and as plainly as if he ſhuld call you by your name, and ſay, come <hi>M. P. E.</hi> I ſpeake vnto thee by name.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Aduiſe your ſelfe well, that he that knowes you calls you. Eſa. 43.1. Feare not, for I haue redeemed thee, I haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee by thy name, thou are mine.</note> you will grant, that in thoſe wordes (which you finde thus written, in <hi>Mathew chap. 11. verſe 28. Come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me all you, that are weary and laden,</hi> Chriſt Ieſus calleth al ſinners generally,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:377:20"/>you are one among the reſt. Therefore he cals you. For he ſaith, <hi>he came to cal ſinners to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in the forenamed wordes he cals ſuch ſinners onely particularlie and by name as are wearie and laden with their ſinnes.
<note place="margin">Iudge you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be called.</note> Are your ſinnes pleaſant to your palat, and ſweete vnto your taſte? Doeth the remembrance of your ſinnes make you laugh, as though ye were tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, when you thinke vpon them? Is it the ioy and pleaſure of your ſinnes, which drawes ſo great ſtore of falt teares from your eies, and fetcheth ſo many deepe ſighes from your heart: Doe your ſinnes lie vpon your conſcience like ſome little light feather: or rather do they not preſſe and holde you downe as a woonderfull weightie burthen: If you be in this caſe, then may you know, if you will know that which ſhall doe you good, that he ſpeakes to you by name, and ſaith vnto you, <hi>come</hi> boldly and feare not, I will eaſe thee of all thoſe thy ſinnes, which are ſo great a burthen to thy conſcience, and will giue thee a gracious generall pardon in my death and paſſion. Moreouer, I will from top to toe couer and cloath thee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:377:21"/>with the rich robes of mine owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe vnto the full aſſurance of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</p>
            <p>The third obiection followeth,
<note place="margin">The third obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; anſwer. The troubled mind complaines of the weakneſſe of faith.</note> that your faith is weake, and ſo weake, as you are fully perſwaded there is no childe of God hath ſo weake a faith as you haue. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it fareth with you as it doth with one that is greatly troubled with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tooth-ach, gout, ſtone, or ſome ſuch ſtrong diſeaſe, who being in verie great paine, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie thereof cries out, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any creature in the world ſo cruellie tormented. And why ſaith he ſo: forſooth becauſe he feeles his own paine, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans beſide:
<note place="margin">Enery man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of his owne paine.</note> therefore he ſpeakes of that which himſelf feeleth, and not of that which he doth not feele. For there be a great many mo as greatly tormented as he: but he thinkes not ſo, becauſe he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th not feele it ſo: Thus do you deale, you are greatly troubled with the weaknes of your own faith which you feele: therfore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your feeling you complaine,
<note place="margin">Many deere ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God are greatly greeued for the weaknes of their faith.</note> that none hath ſo weake a faith as you haue: not withſtanding there be a great number be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides your ſelfe, who are as much troubled
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:377:21"/>this way as you. But I will take your own words. You ſay your faith is weake. Yea, then you grant you haue faith. And therefore ſay I, or rather the Lord himſelf for your comfort, you cannot poſſiblie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>For God ſo loued the world,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.16.</note> that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him might not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But your faith (as you ſay) is ſo weake, that you cannot thinke it to be anie faith at all.
<note place="margin">A weake faith is a good faith, therefore make much of it, and labour to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it.</note> And I againe doe anſwer you with a better warrant than your thought, that a weake faith is a faith, yea a good and a ſound faith. The weakenes of faith doth not take away the nature and beeing of faith, that becauſe there is weakneſſe in it, therefore it ſhould ceaſe to be a faith. Will you ſay a weake man is no man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his weakeneſſe: No,
<note place="margin">A weake man is a man.</note> for he is a man though neuer ſo weake, as long as there is any life and breath in him. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth his weakeneſſe take away his goodnes: for he may be a verie good man although he be verie weake: So ſay I of your faith, the weakeneſſe thereof takes not away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes. It is a good, a ſound and a liuely faith, although it be weake. I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:377:22"/>neuer yet heard of anie beleeuing man or woman,
<note place="margin">Weakneſſe of faith, a generall complaint of all the godlie.</note> but haue complained of the weakneſſe of their faith. Nay for my part I haue marked it in ſundrie examples, that the more godly and beleeuing, the more they haue complained. I coulde from mine owne experience, name diuerſe to proue this paint, and ſome of them well knowne vnto your ſelfe. But I wil name ſome one or two out of the Scriptures, and leaue the reſt to your owne good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>You reade in the Goſpell of Marke the ninth chapter and foure &amp; twentieh verſe of ſo good and faithfull a man,
<note place="margin">marke 9.24. Example of a weake faith in a verie good man.</note> as you wil your ſelfe confeſſe, hee had a true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere faith, becauſe hee ſaide vnto Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Lord, I beleeue.</hi> Neuertheleſſe, this good man was ſicke of your diſeaſe, and felt his faith to be weake, yea verie weake, and therfore he intreates the Lord Ieſus very earneſtly, yea crying out with tears ſaith, <hi>Lord help my vnbeleef, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again you reade in Saint Lukes Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, the ſeuenteenth chapter and fift verſe, of the holie Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">The Apoſtles weake in ſaith.</note> whom our Sauiour Chriſt had choſen to preach, and by their preaching to beget faith in others: yet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:377:22"/>euen theſe men doe in like maner find and feele great want and weakneſſe in their owne faith. For which cauſe they put vp their humble ſupplication vnto their Lord and maſter Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>that he would increaſe their faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that now you ſee verie plainly,
<note place="margin">Weakeneſſe and wants will waite vpon vs to our graue.</note> there is no cauſe, why you ſhould too much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage your ſelfe, with the conſideration of the weakeneſſe of your faith. Becauſe the beſt and moſt faithfull ſeruants of God, doe halt of this ſore as well as you, and ſhall doe as long as they liue in this world. For there is no perfection of any good grace in this life.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>We ſee and know in part,</hi> and therefore muſt needes alſo beleeue and practiſe in part. Perfection is no where to bee found but in heauen,
<note place="margin">Weakeneſſe of faith a ſpeciall meanes to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs.</note> that that we may long to be there, and ſo bee fully perfect. God vſeth this as a holie and good meanes rightly to humble you and many of his deare children for your good, that by the true feeling of this weakeneſſe, and many other infirmities, you may ſee how much neede you haue to runne continually for ſtrength and ſuccor at the handes of your ſweete Sauiour, who hath throughlie ſupplied all your
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:377:23"/>wants, and who will ſo ſtrengthen you, that your faith (though neuer ſo weake to your owne feeling) may neuer faile you. For which purpoſe I would haue youe to lay ſure holde of theſe wordes full of ſweete comfort, deliuered vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by out Sauiour Chriſt, for the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of all the faithfull. <hi>Simon, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.31.</note> Sathan hath deſired to winnow you as wheate,
<note place="margin">All the faithfull are as deare to Chriſt as Peter.</note> but I haue prayed for thee that thy faith faile not.</hi> Marke I pray you, how Ieſus Chriſt promiſeth to pray for Peter, and not for him onely, but for all the faithfull. For is hee onelie Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Sauiour?
<note place="margin">He prayeth for all the faithful as wel as for Peter, and for you.</note> is he not alſo the Sauiour of all the faithfull in the world? Is hee not your Sauiour as well as Peters? yes truly. Then he will pray for you alſo. For ſo he ſayth in that moſt ſweete prayer which hee makes to his heauenly father, for all the faithfull which ſhall beleeue in him to the worlds ende.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.20.</note> 
               <hi>I pray not for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhal beleeue in mee through their worde.</hi> And if hee in whom onelie the father is wholie and altogither well pleaſed,
<note place="margin">Math. 3.17.</note> and for whoſe ſake hee can not bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with you, doe praie for you,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:377:23"/>ſhall not hee bee heard, and his prayer fullie graunted: Yes it can not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied.</p>
            <p>But yet you ſay hee ſpeakes to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<note place="margin">Chriſt in Petes ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes to al the faithfull by name.</note> and promiſeth to pray for him by name. Yea, and that is as much as if he ſhould call you by your name, and ſay that he will pray for you, and for ſo manie as Satan hath any deſire to winow. But ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath a great deſire not. onely to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now Peter, but all the reſt of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full alſo. For ſo are Chriſts words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Sathan deſires to winow, not thee,
<note place="margin">Sathans malice in deadly againſt all the faithfull.</note> but you,</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, his malice is not againſt one alone, but againſt all. Therefore as all muſt looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſo Chriſt promiſeth to praie for ſo many as are windowed, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie for you, becauſe you can tell that you are winnowed. And whereas it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord thus to winow and ſift your faith, you may be ſure not to looſe, but to gaine thereby. For this you know, the more the good corne is fanned, and winowed, the cleaner it is; and the oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner golde is put into the fining-pat, the more pure and excellent it is. To this end therefore are you fined after this manner,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:377:24"/>
               <hi>that the triall of your faith being much more precious then golde that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.7.</note> though it bee tried with fire, might bee found vnto your praiſe and honour, and glorie at the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I come to anſwere a fourth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of yours.
<note place="margin">The fourth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning praier,</note> That you cannot pray. What, can you not pray at all? can yee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer pray? Yes you thanke God for his mercie, you can pray ſometimes, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo often, nor ſo zealouſly as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and as your neede enforceth you. Sometimes you pray,
<note place="margin">Cold praier bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then no praier.</note> but verie coldlie, and with verie little or no feeling. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time you pray more earneſtly, and for all that, you find ſmall comfort. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times though you doe what you can, you can not praie for your life. This is as I knowe by ſome wofull experience a verie iuſt and true complaint: yet I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber when I demanded whether you could praie at anie time, you could not denie but you could pray ſometime, and I am perſuaded with good feeling and ſweete comfort to your ſoule. Whereupon I proue once againe to your conſcience, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:377:24"/>you haue a true faith vnto ſaluation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe prayer is an vndoubted, and plaine fruit of a liuely faith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13.</note> accompanied with euerlaſting ſaluation: for <hi>whoſoeuer calleth vpon the name of the Lord ſhal be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Praier is not a common gift,
<note place="margin">Prayer no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon but a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all giſt giuen to the elect.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all, but a ſpeciall gift, proper on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the elect, as faith and repentance. The Apoſtle ſaieth, <hi>All men haue not faith, 2. Theſſalon. 3.2.</hi> ſo ſay I, all men haue not the gift to pray. A wicked man can not pray, becauſe he can not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, for praier is a moſt excellent fruit of faith. The vngodly haue not this gift in truth, or in any good meaſure, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they haue many other excellent gifts of wiſdome, councell, &amp; learning, yet they want this, which the Prophet doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auouch, ſaying of them, <hi>that they call not vpon God:</hi> as though he ſhould ſay, they do many other things, but they doe not this, and no maruell, for indeede they cannot, becauſe they want that ſpirite which ſhould teach them to pray, for the ſpirit helpeth our infirmities, and praieth in vs, yea this ſame ſpirite of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which hath wrought a gracious mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:377:25"/>of Faith and Repentaunce in your heart hath taught you alſo to pray, and to take ſo great delight therein, that you are glad when you can pray your ſelfe, or can be partaker with others when they pray.</p>
            <p>But you ſay ſometimes you cannot pray at all,
<note place="margin">Praier is not a common gift.</note> and therefore you doubt your ſelfe very much.
<note place="margin">The godly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwayes pray as they would.</note> If you could pray when you would, and as you would (beare with my plainneſſe, for I ſpeake from the feeling of mine owne heart) you would be proude, you would thinke it were but a gift of nature, in your owne power and no gift of God: ſo ſhould God looſe his glorie, ſo ſhould you ſoone forget the right vſe of a notable bleſſing, and forget alſo to be thankfull. Nowe you haue it but ſeldome, or not ſo often as you would your ſelfe, you knowe from whome you receiue it, and when you haue it, you vſe it with more reuerence, and make more account of it, you take more ioy in it: and when you want it, you groane to God for it the more earneſtly. It is verie needefull and much for your profit,
<note place="margin">The want of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſings and graces is very needefull and profitable.</note> that the Lord would excuſe the beſt of his ſeruants with the want of manie bleſſings and graces both for their
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:377:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>bodies and ſoules.
<note n="1" place="margin">To be ſicke,</note> It is good ſome times to be ſicke, that we may knowe how good a thing it is to enioy the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of health.
<note n="2" place="margin">Hungerbitten,</note> It is good ſometimes to be hungerbitten, that our meate may be the more ſauourie, that we may be the more thankfull for our foode, that we may receiue and vſe it more reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and the more willingly releeue ſuch as ſtand in neede. It is good for vs ſome nights to be abridged of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſleepe,
<note n="3" place="margin">To want ſleepe,</note> that we may know there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.2</note> that <hi>it is the Lord who giues reſt vnto his beloued.</hi> It is verie meete we ſhould ſometimes be troubled in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<note n="4" place="margin">To haue a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled concience. Peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a pretious bleſſing.</note> that we may knowe how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a bleſſing that is aboue all others, to enioy the peace of conſcience, and to labour aboue all things to attaine to it, and to maintaine the ſame. It is good for vs ſometimes to be cleane to ſeeke hawe to praie, that when we can praie, we may be the more humble, reuerent and thankful.</p>
            <p>But if you like to ſtand vpon this point to vrge the ſame againſt your ſelfe, I will as in the ſight of God, to his glorie, and mine owne ſhame, confeſſe the truth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:377:26"/>vnto you, as it is with me in this thing. I haue more cauſe a thouſand fold, to doubt my ſelfe herein, then you haue, by reaſon of the great calling which the Lord hath layed vpon me, being a miniſter and teacher of the word. Therefore the <hi>Lord be mercifull vnto me a wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> For my wicked euill heart is ſo narow and baren in prayer, that many times I cannot pray at all. And this fals out not onelie in my priuate meditations betweene God and mine owne ſoule, but in my dailie prayers with my houſhold, wherein I haue beene forced for the moſt part to vſe,
<note place="margin">This hath beene in former time, now through Gods grace it is otherwiſe, yet perfourmed in great weakeneſſe, and with many wants, beſides ſome ſpeciall ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe an other way ſufficient to abate the pride of my heart, and to keepe me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> and that almoſt word for word, a ſhort prayer, which I haue ſet downe in a ſhort Cathechiſme for the helpe and furtherance of ſuch as are vnder my charge. And if vpon ſome ſpeciall occaſion offered, I indeuour my ſelfe to pray otherwiſe, it is ſuch poore, drie, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſillie ſtuffe, both for words and matter, that after I haue prayed, I am a great while maruelouſly tormented in conſcience. And I ſhould be vtterly aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that you or any other ſhould come within the hearing of my babling praiers. And aſſuredlie, were it not that I felt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:377:26"/>ſome more gracious aſſiſtance, from the Lord in thoſe prayers, which are offered vp in my publike miniſterie, I could haue ſmall aſſurance of Gods louing fauour towardes mee. This I confeſſe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the truth, that you may know you are no more alone in this point, than in the former, and to intreate you to pray for me, following the good aduiſe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie apoſtle Saint Iames, who counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs,
<note place="margin">Iames 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>to confeſſe our ſinnes one to an other, and to pray for one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas ſay you, how ſhould I pray for you,
<note place="margin">True praier is not a ſet order of fine wordes.</note> when I can not pray for my ſelfe. If you cannot pray in ſet wordes, and in fine order, can you not therefore pray at all? can you not ſigh and groane inwardly, in the true feeling of your ſoul, as one that is ſo greatly oppreſſed with griefe, that he hath not a tongue to vtter that which he hath within his minde. If you can ſigh and grone, after this maner, be of good comfort. For you haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned long ſince, from ſome of your faithful teachers, who haue many times ſoundlie taught this point from the word of God, and that of purpoſe for the relief of weake
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:377:27"/>conſciences, that you pray verie effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Your ſighes are prayers which the ſpirite, from whom they proceed, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth right well, yea although there is not ſo much as anie one worde vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to expreſſe them. Wordes are for our vnderſtanding, that we may thereby knowe one anothers meaning. But the hoke ſpirite which is our comfortable ſchoolemaiſter, and ſearcheth the deepe things of God, knowes our meaning and thoughts before we ſpeake, yea although we ſpeake not at all. For as the Prophet Dauid ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.2.</note> 
               <hi>He knowes our thoughts long before.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, the <hi>ſpirite helpeth our infirmities, for we knowe not what to pray as wee ought, but the ſpirite it ſelfe maketh requeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for vs with ſighes, which cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſighes breaking out violentlie from the conſciences of the godlie,
<note place="margin">The ſighes of the Godlie are acceptable prayers.</note> are prayers, and loude cryes, acceptable t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord, and pearcing deepelie into his eares, as appeares in Exodus <hi>14.15.</hi> Where the Lorde demaundeth of Moſes why hee cryed <hi>ſo vnto him,</hi> whereas the wordes of the Text make no mention of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:377:27"/>anie one worde hee ſpake or vttered. I pray you tell mee this one thing,
<note place="margin">A ſimilie.</note> if the childe of your owne bodie, whom you loue dearelie, and which is vnto you as your owne ſoule, ſhall be ſicke, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of paine, ſhall moane him ſelfe vnto you, tell you howe ſicke hee is, where his paine doth holde him, and ſhall entreate you euen as you loue him, to doe what you can to eaſe him, will you not doe it both willinglie and readilie: yea, will you not doe whatſoeuer you are able euerie kinde of way for the eaſe of your deare dearling: But if his paine ſhall encreaſe and grewe ſo great, that it takes awaie his ſpeech, ſo as bee is not able to ſpeake a worde, but to fetch deepe ſighes, and to moane himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you by moſt greeuous groanes, will not theſe groanes pearce your heart more deepelie, and cauſe the bowels of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to yerne in you more ſtronglie, to ſtraine your ſelfe euen to the vttermoſt of all your power to affoorde him as much comfort as is poſſible, both by your ſelfe &amp; by others: ſhall the groning of your child worke great pitie in you, and ſhall not the the mightie groanes of your poore ſicke
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:377:28"/>ſoul, moue the Lord your God to greater compaſſion?
<note place="margin">The Lord excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth al men in goodneſſe and compaſsion and therefore will heare and helpe you readily.</note> If in ſuch a caſe you will be ſo readie to heare and helpe, know you for certentie the Lord will be more readie to heare and helpe, whenſoeuer you ſhall in the anguiſh of your ſoule groane vnto him. For looke how farre he exceeds you and all other in goodneſſe: ſo farre alſo doth he exceede you and all other in mercie and compaſſion.</p>
            <p>Beſide all this, there is no ſacrifice more acceptable in the ſight of God, then the ſighes and groanes of a troubled minde.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51.17. The ſighes of the ſpirit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to be regarded.</note> For ſo ſaith the Prophet. <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a contrite ſpirit, a contrite and broken heart O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> Therefore make as good account of the groanes and ſighes of the ſpirit, as of any prayer you can make, euen in the beſt words you can deuiſe. And for a farewell of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, remember that the godlie and good king Ezekias,
<note place="margin">Ezekias could not pray, but chatter.</note> could not in ſmooth and fine wordes, poure out his prayers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in his great ſickneſſe, but chatter like a ſwallow or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rane, as hee confeſſeth of himſelfe.
<note place="margin">Eſa. 38.14.</note> Conſider al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the poore Publican, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:377:28"/>of himſelfe,
<note place="margin">The Publican prayed feruently but ſaide little.</note> by reaſon of his ſinnes, and feareing to lift his eies toward heauen, could not deliuer his minde at large, in fit, and choiſe words, but with much paine,
<note place="margin">Lu. 18.9, 10, &amp;c.</note> at the laſt he breakes forth after this manner, <hi>O God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> Neuertheleſſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt giueth ſentence on his ſide, that <hi>he went home more iuſtified, then the proud Phariſie,</hi> who had both words and winde at will.</p>
            <p>Your fiſt obiection doth thus offer it ſelfe, <hi>That you cannot leaue ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The fiſt obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and anſwere, of leauing ſinne.</note> And that which doth more trouble you, you cannot leaue thoſe ſinnes, which you haue vowed to leaue, but you fall againe into them. Firſt you reaſon thus againſt your ſelfe, that you can not leaue ſinne. No maruell,
<note place="margin">Sinne cleapes too faſt to our nature to part with it in ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> for although you be one of Godes ſaintes, and haue receiued the ſpirit of ſanctification in meaſure, to fight the Lords battels againſt ſinne, and hell: yet are you no Angell in this world, ſo as you can altogether ceaſſe to ſinne, becauſe you carrie, and ſhall carrie vnto your graue, a bodie, and ſoule ſubiect to ſinne. Therfore you muſt fight this battel
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:377:29"/>euen ſo long as you haue breath and life. This enemie of yours is ſo ſtrong,
<note place="margin">No perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt ouer ſinne vntill death.</note> that he will neuer be fullie ouercome, vntill you haue ouermaſtred him by death. And then you ſhall haue a full and perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt ouer him and all your enemies. In the meane time, plucke vp a good heart, gird you faſt with all your Chriſtian ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
<note place="margin">Chriſtian co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age and armor.</note> put on your complete harneſſe, and euerie part thereof, as you finde it ſet down in the ſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chap. of the Epiſtle writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Epheſians,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.13, 14, &amp;c.</note> take your weapon in one hand, I meane the <hi>ſworde of the ſpirite,</hi> and your buckler in the other, that is to ſay, <hi>the ſhield of faith.</hi> Lay about you luſtily, with all the ſtrength and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you haue. <hi>Yea, bee ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might.</hi> And fear not the iſſue,
<note place="margin">Be carefull to fight Chriſt his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attell, and feare not the iſſue.</note> although you latch and catch many a ſore blowe, no though you be foiled and wounded, becauſe you haue a valiant captaine Chriſt Ieſus your Samour, who hath alreadie himſelfe got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the victorie for you, and who will not ſhrinke one foote from you, vntil ſuch time as you alſo haue gotten the victorie. <hi>For in all theſe things wee are more then conquerours through him that loued
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:377:29"/>vs. Rom. 8.37.</hi> And that you may haue the more courage to fight this field with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fainting, vnderſtand thus much,
<note place="margin">All the faithfull doe fight one and the ſame battell.</note> that all the faithfull doe ioyne hands with you to fight out this battell.</p>
            <p>The holie Apoſtle Paule had recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a great meaſure of ſanctification a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue manie thouſandes of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: yet could not hee get the full ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie ouer ſinne, but that full ſore againſt his will to his hearts griefe hee fell into it. Therefore with ſorrow of ſoule, hee complaines in the ſeuenth Chapter to the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mames.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>That the good which he would he did not,
<note place="margin">Paule fought a blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>die field with ſinne.</note> but the euill which hee would not, that did hee.</hi> And that it may be well vnderſtoode, that this was not onelie a ſharpe hote ſkirmiſh, for a ſhort fit, but a ſet battle to continue to the ende of his life, you may reade howe after ſundrie and diuerſe greeuous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of his owne weakeneſſe, and of the ſtrength of ſinne, as a man that is wearie of his life, for no cauſe but this onely, that he could not leaue ſinne, hee breakes out into theſe wordes of great paſſion.
<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe 24.</note> 
               <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:377:30"/>bodie of this death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poul could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaue ſinne as he deſired.</note> In which ſpeech he doth bewray two things. Firſt that hee could not leaue ſinning, although it was his whole ſtudie, and the onelie thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong manie, which he moſt earneſtlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Therefore he calles himſelfe a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man, becauſe he carries about a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſinne and death. Secondly, that hee had as longing a deſire to ceaſe from ſin, as any man could haue. And therefore hee aſketh this queſtion. <hi>Who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe tell me I beſeech you, is it not thus with you:
<note place="margin">The godly would ſaine leaue ſinne, and ſo would you with all your heart.</note> Would you not faine leaue ſinne if you could, and that with all your heart, are you not wearie of it, and ſore grieued for it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Muſt it not needes bee thus, becauſe you complaine ſo greatly, you can not leaue ſinne: You ſinne in deede, but not willingly, nor of ſet purpoſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſay 5.18.</note> you drawe not ſinne vnto you with cart ropes, as the wicked doe, but you are violentlie drawne by the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and violence of ſinne.
<note place="margin">The godly ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> willingly as the wicked.</note> You hunt not after iniquitie, to purſue and followe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, with the intiſements thereof. But ſinne hunts and purſues you, till you haue loſt both winde, and ſtrength, and ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:377:30"/>it may bee, you are manie times taken priſoner. In which caſe you are no more to bee blamed, then a Souldiour, who in battell is full ſore agaynſt his will taken priſoner of his enemie, which thing is moſt manifeſt to your owne conſcience, becauſe when you are taken, and you perceiue it, you behaue your ſelfe as a man, which is fallen into his enemies hande. For your heart is greeued, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d your ſoule wonderfully troubled, your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eepe departeth from you, you can eate no meate that doeth you good, you take no pleaſure in anie worldlie thing, there is no mirth in you, but you are all heauie and ſad. If you bee in companie, where you are prouoked to bee merrie, you laugh but for companie: for it is but from the teeth forwarde. To bee ſhort, ſo long as you are holden captiue of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſinne, you are wearie of your life. Therefore all your ſtudie is howe you maie breake off the fetters of ſinne,
<note place="margin">The godly ſtudy how to breake off the fetters of ſinne.</note> and bee deliuered, whereto you applie all your wit, power, cunning, and ſkill: And if through the great goodneſſe of God, you get anie aduauntage to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, there was neuer anie fowle more
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:377:31"/>glad of a faire day, or bird that hath broken out of the fowlers net, more ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuil then you are of ſo happie deliuerance. And when you are deliuered you are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer afterwards more carefull a great deale that you fall not againe into your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies hand.</p>
            <p>Againe you make not a trade of ſinne,
<note place="margin">The wicked do trade in ſinne.</note> to follow it dayly and houre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e as the workers of imquitie,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.23.</note> who follow it as carefully and continually as any man followes his occupation whereby hee muſt liue.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 1.2.3.</note> But the trade which you follow, and the way wherein you walke with delight, is the continuall medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lawe of God, with an earneſt deſire to practiſe it in your whoſe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.2.</note> Your minde and affections are not ſet vpon the earth, but vppon hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and vpon thoſe things which may bring you to heauen.
<note place="margin">It is better with you then you thinke for, and therefore be thankfull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heere vp your heart in the Lord.</note> Therefore in the true acknowledgement of Gods great mercy towards you, you may with peace to your ſoule ſaie with the Apoſtle Paul in the ſeuenth chapter to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans and the fiue and twentieth verſe, <hi>I thanke God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe in my mind I ſerue the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:377:31"/>lawe of God, although in the fleſh,</hi> that is in that part, which is vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>I ſerue the lawe of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching that other point, namely that you <hi>fall often and againe into that ſin, which you haue vowed neuer to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit againe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is no wonder in this corruption to ſinne often in the ſame ſinne.</note> for as much as the ſame is againſt your wil through great infirmitie, and not of anie ſet purpoſe, although I wiſh you in anie wiſe to be as carefull as may be therein, and to vſe all good and holie meanes of watching ouer your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and auoiding all thoſe occaſions,
<note place="margin">All good meanes muſt be vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euerie ſinne.</note> whereby you may bee drawen forward into a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the leaſt ſinne, by praying, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and ſuch like holie exerciſes, whereby you may be better ſtrengthened againſt all aſſaultes of ſinne: yet would I not haue you to diſcourage your ſelfe too much with the conſideration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
<note place="margin">Conſider wiſell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and apply with reuerence.</note> For this you knowe that one which walketh in a ſupperie way or vpon ice, may againſt his will, yea though hee looke neuer ſo well to his feete, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie take the firſt, but the ſecond, and the third fall, yea manie falles, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that he thinketh to ſet his foote mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:377:32"/>
Abraham although hee was the father of the faithfull,
<note place="margin">Abraham fell more than once into one ſinne.</note> and for his godlineſſe highlie commended in the Scripture: yet through great weakeneſſe, lyed firſt in Egypt to Pharao, in denying Sarah to be his wife,
<note place="margin">Theſe examples are to comfort ſuch as woulde leaue ſinne, and not to encourage any to liue in ſinne.</note> Geneſis the twelfth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and thirteenth verſe. Againe hee fell into the ſelfe ſame ſinne vnto Abimelech, the king of Gerar, Geneſis the twentie chapter, and ſecond verſe. Sarah alſo gaue her conſent both times, and was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the ſinne. Iſaac their ſonne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke occaſion, ſo readilie coyned a lie, as if his father and mother had not only by practiſe, but by precept taught him to lie. I knowe both what I ſay, and to whom I ſpeake, for as theſe examples and ſuch like, may not, nor ought not, to make vs bolde to runne headlong, or to continue with delight in anie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great or ſmall: (for then w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto vs) ſo they ſerue to comfort vs, that wee ſtand not ouermuch amazed at our daylie ſlippes in ſinne.</p>
            <p>Nowe followeth a ſixt obiection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning hardneſſe of heart,
<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ixt obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning hardnes of heart.</note> That you can not profite by the worde preached, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:377:32"/>therefore thinke it were as good or better not to heare at all, as to heere to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and profit. For hardneſſe of heart, which is the firſt branch of this obiection, I anſwere that it is a principal part of the corruption of the old man, which clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth faſt vnto our nature, and is one of our mortall enemies, which will haunt vs vnto the death.
<note place="margin">Hardneſſe of har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll hang vpon vs and haunt vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the death.</note> For our faith ſhall be exerciſed therewithal, as long as we ſhall liue in this world. Therefore our beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie is to arme our ſelues with the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proofe before rehearſed, and to buckle with this aduerſarie,
<note place="margin">Looke well to your atmour.</note> whoſe edge and courage, by little and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated. And for your encoragement this I ſay, that fleſh and bloud hath not ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your eies to ſee this to be a ſinne, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touched your heart, with a miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iking thereof:
<note place="margin">Bleſſe gods narre, that now you ſee and greeue for that ſinne which in former times you neither ſaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor greened for.</note> for then you might long ago haue found out this and manie other ſinnes, when they raigned in you more ſtrongly, and caried you headſong, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſiſtance or miſliking into much euil, to commit ſin with great greedines. But then you could find no fault at all with your ſelfe, nay you thought your ſelf
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:377:33"/>in as good caſe as was poſſible.
<note place="margin">Your caſe all one with the Apoſtle Paul. Ro. 7.9. &amp;c. Acts 26.9.</note> And no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uell, becauſe you were blinded through the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rkneſſe of your owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and reaſon, ſo as you could iudge no colours.</p>
            <p>Now, through Gods goodneſſe, for the welfare of your ſoule, your eies which were blind, are opened to ſee thoſe things which you neuer ſaw before, and your heart is touched with a wonderfull miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking of that which before you leued. Yea indeede you muſt needes confes,
<note place="margin">Giue God leaue and he will helpe that which you can not.</note> you ſee and feele your hardneſſe of heart, but you cannot helpe nor amend it. No, but the Lord both can and wil helpe to amend whatſoeuer is amiſſe in his time. In the meane time,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.14.</note> do what you can, <hi>be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, tarie the Lords leaſure, wait vpon him, and he ſhall comfort thine heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where you ſay,
<note place="margin">A generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the beſt.</note> you cannot profit by the word of God preached, that is alſo a generall complaint of all ſuch as are moſt carefull to profit. But your owne words do prooue againſt your ſelfe, that you doe profit. For if you profited not, how comes it to paſſe that you haue found out this fault, that you cannot profit. It is not the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:377:33"/>manner of ſuch as doe not receiue profit by the word preached, to find fault, but to pleaſe and flatter themſelues moſt, when they profite leaſt. Therefore this is a great argument and ſound proofe of your profiting,
<note place="margin">The complaint of not profiting is verie profitable, becauſe it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes you carefull to profite.</note> in that you can thus blame your ſelfe, that you doe not profit. And it pleaſeth the Lord thus to exerciſe you and the reſt of his beloued ones, with the feeling hereof, not to diſcourage you, but that this may be as a whetſtone to ſharpen your ſtomake, to heare with greater conſcience, and as a ſpurre to make you more egar vpon the word, when it is preached, that the oftener you heare, you may deſire more and more, to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite by hearing.</p>
            <p>But where as in the end,
<note place="margin">As you loue your ſoule take heede of this temptati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> you throwe downe this logge in your owne way, that it were good, not to heare at all, I am to giue you ſpeciall warning, as you tender the ſaluation of your owne ſoule, to take heede howe you giue conſent to that temptation, in the leaſt thought of your heart, for it is a ſtrong enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sathan, to bewitch you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and a choiſe baite to catch your ſoule
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:377:34"/>in euerlaſting deſtruction.
<note place="margin">The deuill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching (more than holy water) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ouerthr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> weth his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> He knowes this as well as anie man can tell him, that the word preached is the onelie moſt principall meanes, which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſtrengthen you againſt the whole batterie and force of al his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Hee knowes alſo that from thence you daylie gather courage againſt him. Whether it be thus or not, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to your conſcience. And if you haue found this powerfull worke in your owne ſoule, then ſo often as hee ſhall thruſt in this temptation ſay vnto him <hi>auoyde Sathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 4.10.</note> for thou laboureſt to murther my precious ſoule, by withdrawing me from the meanes of my ſaluation.</p>
            <p>But howe doth he vrge this point a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you,
<note place="margin">The deuils cruſt in reaſoning.</note> and with what reaſons. Firſt becauſe you doe not feele profit preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Secondlie becauſe you doe not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite ſo much as you ſhould. Nowe marke I beſeech you the deuils craft in reaſoning. Firſt you feele no profit by the word preſentlie ſo ſoone as you heare it preached: therefore you doe not profit at all. You feele not profite preſentlie, therefore you ſhall neuer feele profite.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:377:34"/>You ſhall ſee this cunning laied open to your vnderſtanding in a familiar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, after this manner.
<note place="margin">The deuils cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning laide wide open by ſenſible reaſons.</note> A ſicke man hath Phiſicke giuen him to helpe his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: He is not helped preſentlie ſo ſoone as hee hath taken it: Therefore he ſhall neuer haue helpe. The huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth ſowe his ſeede, and caſts it into the ground, that it may growe and bring forth fruit: But it growes not ſo ſoone as it is ſowen: Therefore it will not growe at anie time, neither ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee euer reape anie croppe of his ſeede.</p>
            <p>Againe hee reaſoneth thus againſt you, you profit not ſo much as you ſhould, or not alwayes alike: Therefore you profit not at all. This is as if one ſhould reaſon after this faſhion. One a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re of corne ſome yeare brings forth fiue, tenne, twentie, or a hundred fold: But it doth not ſo euerie yeare: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it brings forth nothing at all. Some yeares an occupier gaynes a hundred pound by his trade: Hee gaynes not ſo much euery yeare: Therfore he gains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Thus the deuil reaſoneth with you
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:377:35"/>therefore be your ſelfe iudge: of his maner of reaſoning, and the Lord in mercie giue you wiſedome, in all things to take heed of his wilineſſe, that you be not by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie way abuſed.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth and laſt obiection is,
<note place="margin">The laſt obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning euill thoughts.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning euill thoughts, which ariſe in the minde, wherewith I know, ſome are not a little troubled, for comfort of whoſe weake conſciences, which are many times ouer much greeued by the conſideration thereof: I anſwere thus from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie the ſeuenteenth Chapter and ninth verſe:
<note place="margin">Ierem. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>that the heart is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, and wicked aboue all things, who can know it?</hi> By which place (if my iudgement doe not much abuſe mee) this one leſſon may be rightlie and kindly gathered, that when the beſt men and women haue done their beſt, to their beſt power, they ſhall neuer attaine, or come to the perfect,
<note place="margin">The heart is like a bottomleſſe pit which can neuer be drawen drie.</note> and full knowledge of' all the corruption, and filthineſſe which is there hatched, and harboured: becauſe it is like vnto a bottomles pit, which can neuer be drawne drie. Hereupon I reaſon thus.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:377:35"/>If we ſhall neuer in the whole courſe of our life, come to the through, and full knowledge of all that venemous poiſon, which is deepe rooted in the dungeon of our vnderſtanding: how then ſhall it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be poſſible for vs, to attaine to the perfect reformation of ſo manie diſorders, as are there to be found.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 6.5.</note> Againe the Lord himſelfe ſaith, <hi>That all the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the thoughts of mans heart, be euill, onelie euill, and that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie.</hi> If all be euill by nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we be regenerate, and borne a new by a ſecond birth of the ſpirit, and word, and that continuallie: then no maruell if ſome be euill, and that continually after our regeneration. Becauſe wee be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed but in part,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>and we haue ſo put on the new man, which after god is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in true holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as that we ſhal neuer cleane, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>put off the old man with all his deceiueable luſtes, vntil we put off this fleſh, and that by death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this one point ſtandeth a great part of our Chriſtian warfare, wherein we are at all ſeeles and ſeaſons, to ſtand
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:377:36"/>vpon our garde,
<note place="margin">This is our taske to our dying day, to fight againſt our affections which are our deadly foes.</note> and to watch with all diligence, in withſtanding the euill affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and thoughts of our hearts, which as Peter ſaith <hi>fight againſt our ſoules.</hi> For theſe be ſuch ſpitefull enemies, as lodge themſelues cloſe euen in the cloſet of our heart,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2 11.</note> they eate and drinke with vs,
<note place="margin">Our vnruly and lordly lufts do yawe vs continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</note> they ſleepe and wake with vs, they ride and goe with vs, they goe out and in with vs: to bee ſhort, when our oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> enemies, the worlde, and the diuell doe graunt vs ſome time of truce, their will affoord vs no peace, becauſe they ſit ſo neare vs, as that euermore they are at hand readie to aſſault vs,
<note place="margin">Faith and praier are our beſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</note> both before and behinde, and on euerie ſide. Therefore we are to the vttermoſt of our power, to arme our ſelues ſtrongly againſt them by faith, by prayer, and all other good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie meanes. That wee maie daylie get ground of them, and through Gods grace, ouermaiſter them in ſome good meaſure, to our euerlaſting comfort. The rather becauſe the wiſe man ſaieth. <hi>He that is ſlowe to anger,
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 16 32.</note> is better then a mightie man, and hee that ruleth his owne minde, is better than hee that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:377:36"/>winneth a citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But euen now while we are ſpeaking of euill thoughts, there comes in one,
<note place="margin">A wofull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thoughts.</note> with a moſt lamentable complaint, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, O ſir, I am ſo troubled this way, as I thinke there was neuer anie childe of God ſo grieuouſlie troubled. For I haue ſuch wicked and blaſphemous thoughts, as make my fleſh to tremble, and all my bones to ſhake, yea they are ſuch as they almoſt driue me to diſpaire, when I thinke vppon them. For they ſtrike not at men, but at God himſelfe. They exalt themſelues againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Trinitie, and ſome of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the bleſſed, and holie Scriptures. What they bee in partieular, I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſpeake. If you bee aſhamed ſo much as to name them, then I perceiue you take no great liking of them, neither doe you meane to entertaine them. And therefore I anſwere in fewe wordes, they ſhall not be able to hurt you.
<note place="margin">Pſalme 66.28.</note> 
               <hi>If I regard wickednes in my heart</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>God wil not heare me.</hi> He doth not ſay, if there be any wickedneſſe at all in my heart, or anie thought of wickedneſſe.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:377:37"/>(For who can ſay,
<note place="margin">It is one thing to haue euil thoghts, and another, to like of them, and delight in them.</note> 
               <hi>my heart is cleane,</hi>) but <hi>if I regard wickednes,</hi> that is, if I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it, or meane to nouriſh it within me, then I am ſure the Lord will not heare my prayer, nor ſhew me any fauour. But as if the Prophet ſhould ſay, and as I am ſure you doe ſay, that is farre from me, to take delight in any ſuch vngodlie, and blaſphemous thoughts, yea ſo farre, as I am not more greeued for any thing, then for this, that any ſuch thought ſhould come into my minde. And therefore hee and you, and you as well as he, may bee vndoubtedly perſwaded, the Lord will neither reiect you, nor your prayers, which in Chriſt his name, you ſhall offer vp vnto him.</p>
            <p>And whereas you thinke it ſo ſtrange, to haue ſo euill thoughts, to ariſe in your minde, and that you are perſwaded, there are no moe ſo tempted beſide your ſelfe, I anſwere vpon mine owne knowledge, you are therein greatlie deceiued. There bée manie who are euen as much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the ſame, or with as euill. And this I dare auouch,
<note place="margin">The moſt godly are not free from euill thoughts.</note> that the moſt godlie are not free, but are ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:377:37"/>moſt vngodly thoughts,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.10. and pſal. 51.5.</note> although they yeeld not vnto them. Firſt becauſe they as well as others, doe carrie with them, a curſed corrupt nature, which is the roote from whence all euill ſpringeth. Secondly, becauſe they haue ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, as will not ſpare to tempt them to the greateſt euill, yea, to this,
<note place="margin">Iob tempted to curſe God, not in his heart, but with his mouth. Iob 1.7.</note> then the which there can be nonegreater, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to curſe God: as the iuſt and holy man Iob was tempted. But as that good man withſtoode the temptation, ſo doe they fight againſt euerie euill motion, and are preſerued.</p>
            <p>Yet there is one thing more concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning euil thoughts, which is, that you can not be rid of them, but that euer, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none they come into your minde. To this I anſwere,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the ſooner you checke them, and the more ſtrongly you reſiſt them, the ſooner a great deale, ſhall you bee rid of them. Firſt, you muſt reſiſt: for,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>reſiſt the deuil and he will flie from you.</hi> And heere marke, that this reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, muſt be by the word, and by praier.
<note place="margin">The ready way to be rid of euill thoughts, is to reſiſt them.</note> Secondlie, you muſt reſiſt egerlie, and ſpeedilie. And therefore as Dauid haſted
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:377:38"/>to fight againſt Goliah,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.48.</note> and with courage ſlang a ſtone ſo hard, that it ſtacke faſt in the foreheade of the vncircumciſed Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtim: ſo muſt you ſpeedilie ſtrike at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſuch thought, ſo ſoone as you ſhall perceiue the ſame to put out his head, and once to ariſe in your minde. And as Ieſus Chriſt, being tempted of the diuell to fall downe and worſhip him,
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.10.</note> at the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant gaue him his anſwere, ſaying, <hi>auoid Sathan:</hi> ſo muſt you giue them a preſent anſwere, and ſend them packing to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of hell, from whence they come, and whither you are in all haſte to returne them. If when you haue vone what you can, you finde your ſelfe too weake for them, &amp; that they be too hard a great deale for you, then turne your captaine Chriſt Ieſus to them, who hath ſo fullie conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, as that howſoeuer they ſhall aſſault you continuallie, and manie times foile you, yet ſhall they neuer get the full victorie ouer you, but you in your captaine ſhal be more then a conquerour ouer them and all the reſt of your deadlie enemies,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> for <hi>Chriſt was deliuered to death for our ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> and roſe againe for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:377:38"/>To him therefore be glorie for euer and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue the pledge of my good will towards you &amp; manie others, which I haue not done to exclude ame grace or bleſſing of comfort which you may receiue in greater meaſure, from your owne god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſtor (moſt careful of your eſtate) but that you may more highly account of ſo excellent graces of God in him. And that what ſoeuer is wanting in this my poore treatiſe, may by him bee more fullie ſupplied.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
